So you want to write a book. I
know the feeling. I've been writing books for more
than 40 years. Now there's a lot
of people out there on the internet and
elsewhere that will try to tell you that
writing a book is easy. You can do it
fast. They've got five steps to writing
a bestseller. I'm not promising you a
bestseller, but I do have 13 foundational
steps that you're going to need to
follow if you're going to write a book.
Speed is not the point. Quality is the
point. So the first thing you're going
to want to do is establish your writing
space. When I first started, I was a young
father and I had no space. I had to take
a plank and put it between two kitchen
chairs, which I set in front of the couch
in the living room, and then I sat
on that couch in front of a manual
typewriter, and that's how I worked. That
was my space. Wherever it is, establish it.
It could be in a Starbucks. It could be
in your car if you have to. And you
should never say that you don't have a place
to write. I can remember being in
the newspaper business. There were 40 of us
in the same room, and back in those
days people smoked in that room. So we had
smoke, we had noise, we had
clacking typewriters. A writer can write anywhere,
but you want to establish what you need.
So if you need solitude, make sure you
find a place in your house where you
can shut the door, where you can turn off
media, and you can have privacy and
silence and whatever you need to write.
And the more you can afford, the better you'll do,
especially if you're a writer. So if
you're a writer, you're going to need to
have a lot of space. You need to have a
lot of space. You need to have a lot of
space. So you can write in a room with
a lot of space, as far as equipment and
space. The second important step is to
assemble your writing tools. And really, you
don't need too many. Say you're writing
in a restaurant. All you need is your
laptop and a comfortable chair. Now, you
may have to take whatever chair they've
got, but learn how that works for you. Do
you need to take a cushion from home so
you can sit up straight? Your back
and your neck are important to your writing.
You're going to be spending a lot of
hours in front of that computer. So don't
scrimp on your computer, and when
you're home, don't scrimp on your computer.
Don't scrimp on your chair. And then make
a list of all the things you're going to
need while you're writing, especially at home.
If you need paper clips or a stapler
or whatever, make sure you have all those
within arm's length so you don't get distracted
by having to look for things when you need them.
Okay, the third important thing you want to
do is to break the project into small pieces.
The reason that writing a book seems so colossal
is because it is. Writing a book is akin to
eating an elephant. How do you eat an elephant?
One bite at a time. So break the task into
as many small pieces as you can. You have
to realize, yes, it's a four or five hundred
page manuscript in the end, but that's
made up of sentences, paragraphs, chapters. Just
do them one at a time. That's
the way to get a handle on it.
Step number four is to settle on your big idea,
and it needs to be a big idea. If it's
book worthy, it's going to be big concept.
We don't have any room in the marketplace
anymore for small concept book ideas. If it's small,
use it for a blog or an article. But
think how to win friends and influence
people if you're thinking nonfiction. Think Harry
Potter if you're thinking fiction. It has
to be big. I can't overstate the importance
of this. If you try to write a book before
and you ran into a roadblock at the 20 or
30 day mark, or maybe the 20 or 30 page
mark, it could be because your idea wasn't big enough.
How do you know if your idea is big enough
and if it has legs? If it stays with you.
If you tell your spouse or your friend what
your book is about, and every time you tell
them it gets bigger, it's going to be a big
idea. If you try to write a book before and
you ran into a roadblock at the 20 or
30 page mark, that's a book that's going to last
in the marketplace too. Step five is to construct
your outline. And, as you can see, I've done
that on my whiteboard here for you. Now,
this might sound surprising for me to talk about
outlining when I'm known as a pantser, one
who writes by the seat of his pants. Stephen
King is the best known writer who's a
pantser. He says, put interesting characters in difficult
situations and write to find out what happens. I
like to do that, so people think I don't
outline a book.
I don't outline a book at all. But even
we fiction writers who are pantsers have to have
some sort of idea where we're going. Even if
it's on one side of one sheet of paper,
give yourself some direction of where you're
going. Now, some people, especially if you're
a beginning writer, your editor or your agent
may need to see an entire synopsis of your
novel idea. So you'll have to do more of
an outline than you might have to do later. And
agents and editors demand outlines for nonfiction.
There's no writing a nonfiction book without
an outline. They want to know what you're
going to say, how you're going to say it,
where you're getting your information, and what
your points are going to be. Now, we
often talk in fiction about the marathon of
the middle and how that stops everybody. That's
one of the places that I stop to. I
mean, I've written over 190 books and I every time
get to the halfway or three-quarter point and
I wonder, why did I ever think I could
do this?
That's the marathon of the middle and you
can't just survive it or endure it. You have
to thrive in it.
Because the reader is right with you. If
it seems boring to you, your reader is asleep.
So this happens to be true of nonfiction as
well. Now, you'll take care of that with your
outline in nonfiction. You'll know that your middle
has enough good stuff in it. In fiction,
especially if you're a pantser, you better be
sure you're saving a lot of big setups
and payoffs for that marathon of the middle.
And you can do the same in nonfiction. The
same structure works for nonfiction as fiction.
You don't have the same number of elements.
As far as tension and conflict and dialogue
and that type of thing. But you still need
the setup and the payoff. Make your
nonfiction book, say you're writing a nonfiction book
about how to build a model ship. You need
to set it up so that it looks impossible until
your specific solution comes through. That's
your setup and payoff. And remember, don't
be intimidated by an outline. Your outline serves
you, not the other way around. If you've
got an outline and you find yourself drifting
from it or you think the book is working,
that's fine. But if you're not, you're not going
to be able to do it. You're going to
have to work on it. And you're going to have
to work on it. And you're going to have to
work on it. And you're going to have to work
on it. And you're going to have to work on it.
I think you need to create a guideline about
how to move your outline to work in a different
way, better. Change the outline. Don't change
the book. Make your outline work for you.
Okay, I'm back to my desk for point number
six, and that is to set a firm writing schedule
that includes a firm deadline that you keep
sacred. This isn't a thing that hangs up too
many beginning writers. They don't have a
publisher's deadline. So they have to set
their own. And sometimes we tend to fudge
on our own deadlines. Make sure you don't
do that. Keep your deadline sacred.
And the way you do that is you figure
out roughly how many pages you're going to be
writing for your book.
If it's 300, 400, 500, divide that into
the number of days you're allotting yourself to
write.
Now this may change once you get started and
realize how many or how few pages you can
write per day.
If you schedule yourself for 10 pages a
day and find that you're really not comfortable
with more than four or five,
change your schedule, change your deadline.
But once you get it locked in, keep it sacred.
When I was a publisher, I found that
only about one in 100 writers literally meet their
deadlines.
If you just do that, you set
yourself apart from 99 out of 100 writers.
Don't make the mistake of thinking you're
going to find the time to write.
When I have to write, I have
to have something sacrificed from my schedule.
Is it an hour or two of sleep a night?
Is it a concert?
Is it a ball game?
Is it a movie?
Is it a favorite TV show?
How bad do you want this?
I still have a lot of books.
I schedule my days right
on my calendar, on my computer.
I have it color coded.
It's in pink.
And you've caught me when tomorrow I
have to reach the 70,000 word mark.
I have that target there.
I'm at the 67,500 mark now, so I'm
going to have to write 2,500 words tomorrow.
And if I do that for five more days, I'm
going to make my deadline because I keep that deadline
sacred.
Point number seven is to conduct your research.
Now, everybody knows that you
need to have a good schedule.
You need to have a good schedule.
You don't have to do that automatically for nonfiction.
You have to be an expert in what you're
writing in and not just draw in your own experience,
but also show that you've immersed yourself
in all the writing in your field.
But a lot of people miss the fact
that research is just as important for fiction.
In fact, I think it could be even more important.
If you miss a small detail of history or
aircraft or weaponry, you can be sure readers are going
to point this out.
Specificity lends credibility.
to fiction and fiction needs to be believable.
Now once you've done your research you're going
to be tempted to show that off to the reader.
You want to resist that urge. Your research is not your
main course. The story is the main course.
Research is the seasoning that adds that specificity that
gives you credibility and believability. I'm using
a world history chart for my current project
because I'm covering from 2000 BC to the present
day. I need to know when the patriarchs were born
and when they died and how they overlapped.
So make sure your research becomes seasoning and
that it's right because readers notice. Step
number eight is to write a compelling
reader first opener. Give it the time
it deserves because if you can pull off
an important compelling first line it will set the
tone for your entire book. You probably won't write
a more important line than that first
one. Now most first lines fall into
one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight. And
they're not the same. You're going to have to
read one of these categories. Surprising, dramatic
statement, philosophical, or poetic. I'm not going
to give you examples of all of them but let
me just do that for the first two. First surprising
opening in fiction. George Orwell's 1984 begins,
It was a bright cold day in April and
the clocks were striking 13. Would that keep you reading?
It would me. In non-fiction
Elizabeth Gilbert wrote The Last American
Man. Her first line was, By the
time Eustace Conway was seven years old,
he could throw a knife accurately enough
to nail a chipmunk to a tree.
Now for dramatic statement, I'm sure you've
read Toni Morrison's Paradise. Remember that first line?
They shoot the white girl first. That's a
dramatic statement. Now let me read you the
opener to my work in progress. I'm not putting it
in the category of these classics but here's the first one.
It's your mother, Nicole Berman's father said
over the phone. She rose from her
desk at the sound of his voice. What
happened? Hopefully that'll keep you reading. Or can
that вill keep you reading? Now what do I
mean by reader first. Every decision you make in your
manuscript should go through that filter of reader
first. Not you first. Not editor first. Not agent
first. Not reviewer first. Not critic first.
Reader first. Whenever key readers write a he
really liked a book of mine,
I think back to that motto,
think reader first, that I often
will tack right to my screen
on a sticky note.
I want it to be
the best, most compelling, most moving,
most emotional experience they've ever had,
because I'm thinking reader first, not anybody else first.
So think reader first, last, and always.
Step number nine is to fill your story
with conflict and tension.
Readers crave tension.
And yes, this applies to nonfiction as well.
Almost every time a writer shows me their manuscript
and says, I don't know where to go from here,
it's because they got to a
point where the people on the page
are agreeing with each other too much.
And we like that in real life.
It's nice to have pleasant conversations,
talk with your spouse over a meal.
You're talking about how nice a day it is
and what you're going to do.
There's nothing more boring in fiction than that.
So what you want to do is inject that conflict.
Have one of those characters say something
totally different.
Something totally off the wall.
Maybe one says, isn't it a beautiful day?
And the other one says,
oh, sure, you would say that.
All of a sudden, the reader and that character
are going, what was that about?
Where did that come from?
That's conflict.
What's the problem in their relationship?
What's the underlying tension that caused that conflict?
That will keep people turning the pages.
And you want to do that on every page,
even if it's just a matter of someone setting up
an appointment.
They need to see the doctor tomorrow.
There's an implication there that something's coming up,
otherwise why would the author put it in there?
Now in nonfiction, how do you do that?
You don't want unpleasantness.
It doesn't have to be something negative.
It doesn't have to be a
battle or a war or a fight.
Conflict and tension come up in nonfiction simply
by promising and then delivering,
setting up and paying off.
Some of the best nonfiction writers
are ones who spend the first several chapters promising you
what you're going to get
when you finish reading this book,
and then they deliver.
Step number 10 is to turn off your internal editor
while you're writing your first draft.
Most writers I know are perfectionists.
I happen to be one, too.
And so we have that
inner critic sitting on our shoulder,
telling us what's wrong with every word we write.
That inner critic is just you or me,
and that critic needs to be told to shut up.
Now is not the time
to be criticizing your own work.
Always save your editing until the next day, at least.
And the longer you can hold it up, the
moreotypes happen, and I'm glad to have that set up.
The longer you can wait between when you write
it and when you edit it, the better for the
end product.
This is the opening pages of my work
in progress, Dead Sea Rising, my next novel.
I wouldn't show this first draft to my worst enemy.
I don't worry about cliches, redundancies, lacks of logic.
I need to get the story down.
So turn off that internal editor, get your
story down, and then tell yourself that the
next day you can put your perfectionist
cap back on and have at it.
Remember in point number five when
I mentioned the Marathon of the Middle?
I want to make that point 11 and
hit that again because if there's any place you're
going to quit, it's going to
be during the Marathon of the Middle.
This is the toughest spot for me as well.
I've written over 190 books in 40 years.
I hit the Marathon of the Middle every time
and I wonder why did I get into this business?
Okay.
The problem with the Marathon of the Middle
is we've all got great ideas to start and
we can't wait to get to that big finish,
but now we've got a couple hundred pages in the
middle to fill.
And if you just start padding it in
fiction with extra scenes or nonfiction with extra
points, your reader is going to drop off the page.
This is where you don't just survive, you thrive.
For instance, in my current work in progress, Dead
Sea Rising, this is a long novel, 80,000 words.
So the Marathon of the Middle is a good stretch.
How I solved the problem of not letting it
flag in the middle is to alternate from 2000
B.C. to present day and even back to Vietnam.
And I'm setting up my payoffs so well in the
middle that I can hardly wait to get to the
ending.
And the ending will work better because
I didn't just persevere through the Marathon,
I thrived.
Step number 12 is to write a resounding ending.
You want your book to end.
The way a Broadway play ends, when
that curtain comes down with a satisfying thud.
I'm working on my 195th book, so I've got
over 190 books here that all had to have endings
that worked.
Two thirds of my books are novels, one
third are nonfiction, so even nonfiction has to
have that great ending.
How do you make sure your ending doesn't fizzle?
You give it the time it deserves.
I had talked to a lot of writers who've
written their entire manuscript, they get to the end,
and they rush it.
Or they say, I just don't
know how to make it work.
Don't settle for second best.
If it takes longer to write your ending than
the rest of the novel put together, or the
nonfiction book put together, do it.
Do whatever it takes to make it work.
And if you've got several ideas for what might be
best, go for the one that is the most emotional.
Because readers remember what moves them.
My last and most important point, step 13,
is that you need to become a first-person reader.
I'm going to give you a few tips.
Step 13 is to write a resounding ending.
You need to become a ferocious self-editor.
What does it mean to be ferocious?
You know what it means.
It means to be aggressive.
Everything else is for naught if you
don't polish your manuscript to the point where
you're happy with every word.
That doesn't mean it's going to be perfect or
that you don't need an editor if you should
place it with a publisher.
But you need to polish that thing until it sings.
Why?
Because agents and editors can tell within two minutes.
Whether your manuscript is going
to be worth reading or rejecting.
That doesn't sound fair and maybe it isn't
fair, but they have so many things to read.
The competition is so vast.
They've learned to be able to tell within
a page or two whether this has potential or
not.
That puts all the onus on you to self-edit.
People say, should I pay an editor?
If you pay an editor, what is the publisher buying?
Your work or someone else's?
Learn to edit yourself.
Cut to add power.
I have a list of 21 self-editing tips.
You can find them at jerryjenkins.com.
I've been so blessed in my career
that I love to pay it forward.
So I'm sending out free writing tips and writing blogs.
You can find all that at that
website and you'll be ready to go.
The End